<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The question of re-ordination, whether, and how a minister ordained by the Presbytery, may take ordination also by the Bishop? by John Humfrey ...</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11804018</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11804018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 538:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The question of re-ordination, whether, and how a minister ordained by the Presbytery, may take ordination also by the Bishop? by John Humfrey ...</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Williams ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published for the sake of the many concerned, and perplexed about it at this season, without strife, for the promotion only of the Holy Gospel, and peace."</note>
                  <note>Reproduciton of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ordination.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49405:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE QUESTION OF Re-ordination, Whether, and how, a Miniſter Ordained by the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> may take Ordination alſo by the <hi>Biſhop?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Humfrey,</hi> Miniſt.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the ſake of the many concerned, and perplexed about it at this Seaſon, <hi>without ſtrife,</hi> for the promotion only of the holy Goſpel, and Peace.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 15.2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Williams</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Little Britain</hi> without <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49405:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49405:2"/>
            <head>Ad Lectorem.</head>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe was written at firſt in ſix or ſeven Letters, or more, to an intimate friend, according to the date, ſcattered with other matters. Thoſe Papers were ſince returned to the Author to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, ſet together, and ampliſie upon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deliberation. You have them there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in this form, the Superſcription changed from one to many, and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from many as it were to one, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ſo many Sections. If the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer lead on to the latter, and the latter (taking more line) bring perſpicuity and fulneſs to the former, and the whole tend to let ſatisfaction upon the mind, as it is like beſt to take it in, I am bid to tell you, the Author is not farther ſollicitous of the method, which is entended not be <hi>Polemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> for diſpute; but <hi>Medicinal</hi> for the conſcience.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Typographus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49405:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49405:3"/>
            <head>To my Reverend, Pious, and Worthy Brethren in the Miniſtry, who have been Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in theſe Times only by the Presbytery; Grace, Truth and Peace from God the Father and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with the freedom of the Goſpel. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1660.</head>
            <p>WHereas it ſeems to me a thing reaſonable, for a man to give an account of his actions, which may be elſe an occaſion of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to others: I have thought good to write ſome lines about that Buſineſs, which hath a various acceptation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the concerned at this ſeaſon; to wit, the legal <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> (ſo I will
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49405:4"/>call it) according to the Book of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of my former Miniſtry and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation long ſince had, by the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
            <p>Before I go further, I muſt confeſs I have not known, or noted yet, any Book <hi>Pro</hi> or <hi>Con</hi> about this Subject (nor would I, till I had ſcann'd over my own thoughts) to make uſe of, ſo much as to give me either reaſon for it, obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt it, or notion about it, unleſs <hi>obiter</hi> on other matters; ſo that the path is to me quite untrod: Only, I muſt needs ſay, ſince I have done this thing, I find it hath pleaſed God, to exerciſe my ſpirit with many perplexities about it; ſo that I am even forced to find out ſuch a courſe as this, to rid my mind, and give vent to them. Truly, me thinks, from the begining, I have been apt to look upon the matter it ſelf as nothing; yet hath it driven me many times upon my knees, with thoughts in the reflexion, <hi>If it be ſo, why am I thus?</hi> And I do not ſee, what is the end the Lord hath with me therein, unleſs it be,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49405:4"/>that theſe <hi>throws</hi> as it were of mine, are only for the <hi>delivery</hi> of ſomething, for one or other of my Brethrens ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>As for the repeating, or doubling Ordination it ſelf, I do thus judge of it. There are ſome things, which Divines do condemn indefinitely as evill, when being barely conſidered, they ſway more this way, and have a likelyhood rather thereof then good, yet in their nature, are indifferent, (that is, <hi>indifferentia ad unum,</hi> not <hi>ad utrum libet,</hi> as they ſpeak) ſo that, right circumſtances being put, they may be done. I take this matter in hand to be ſuch, which though it be odd and uncouth in its firſt and naked conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, yet, as the caſe complexedly now ſtands, I put it in the number of ſuch things, as <hi>Magna utilitas</hi> (to wit, <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica</hi>) <hi>facit honeſtum;</hi> that is, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of convenience renders tolerable for the time.</p>
            <p>To take liberty as to the ingenuous, This <hi>Re-ordination</hi> may be conſidered, methinks, Notionally, or Morally:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49405:5"/>There is Moral, and Notional good, if I may ſo ſpeak: Moral good, is, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the rule of life, which God hath given us in his Word, or planted in our hearts: Notional good, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in things to their being, (or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) as we apprehend them (or in mens apprehenſions.) So you muſt give me leave to expreſs it. <hi>Re-ordination</hi> now, <hi>Notionally,</hi> I ſuſpect is not good; <hi>Morally,</hi> I judge it, as I have ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> indifferent (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>good,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>bad,</hi> though <hi>unequally,</hi> as it is uſed. Suppoſe a thing born with redundant parts; Here is an odd thing in Nature, <hi>Naturae erratum:</hi> yet as it is God's crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ordered by Providence; it is good, and allowed of her in the world: <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> let me ſay, is, <hi>Ordination</hi> redundant, (an <hi>Erratum</hi> perhaps as to its common notion, or a miſ-ſhape in our apprehenſion) yer if it comes to be ordered by man, to Moral advantage, and the Honor of God (as to the peace and freedom of the Goſpel) the thing is not to be <hi>made away,</hi> but to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49405:5"/>be <hi>allowed</hi> in the Church, as Nature does of ſuch things as theſe, when yet ſhe <hi>likes</hi> them not. Notional good, as natural, muſt give place to Moral good, without queſtion.</p>
            <p>Indeed to dead truly herein, I muſt diſtinguiſh (I think) between the part of thoſe that require this, and thoſe that ſubmit to it. I dare not juſtifie our Church-Rulers in their impoſing hereof, notwithſtanding its near con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to them (<hi>Quid enim facit, exceptâ ordinatione, Epiſcopus, quod Presbyter non facit?</hi> ſayes <hi>Jerome,</hi> and ſome others) becauſe it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſcandalous to the Reformed Churches abroad, and it is ſuppoſed they might remedy it if they would. They know beſt their own juſtifications, Let the fault (if there be any), on Gods name, lye where it is: But as for the part of the Submitter, who for the ſake of his Miniſtry, and preſent ſervice of the Church, does only yield himſelf to obedience and quiet, I do humbly hope the matter is not ſuch, as that he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49405:6"/>ſhould charge himſelf with any great hurt in it. Although in immediate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive acts of Divine Worſhip, nothing be warrantable without command, yet in matters only of Order, it is enough to make things lawful (as I ſuppoſe) that they are required of our Superiors, and no where prohibited in the Word of God. <hi>Quod ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra fidem, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contra bonos mores injungitur, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentèr eſt habendum, &amp;, pro corum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quos vivitur, ſocietate, ſervandum eſt.</hi> Aug. ad Jan. Ep. 118.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi> and purified himſelf with the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Temple, theſe were things I count <hi>indefinitely</hi> unlawful, yet commendable in that caſe. I do chooſe to ſtand on this ground; yet may we draw neerer on <hi>probability.</hi> It may be conjectured, and cannot be denyed as certain, (for very good Divines ſay it) but that <hi>Paul</hi> was confirmed in his calling to the Miniſtry by <hi>Ananias, (Act.</hi> 9. with <hi>Act.</hi> 22.) which is Ordination; and likewiſe <hi>Barnabas</hi> by the Church at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49405:6"/>
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſent him to <hi>Antioch,</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 11.22.) when yet they are both ſeparated after (<hi>Act.</hi> 13.) by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and laying on of hands, unto that farther work they are called to in <hi>Sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus.</hi> How is it like that ſo famous a Miniſter as <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſhould be wholly without Ordination before, unleſs Ordination be not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a thing to the Miniſtry, as we make it? And for the other inſtance of <hi>Paul,</hi> there is more in it: I will not draw out the ſtrength of it, till I come to the chief knot. By the way only, It is a conceit (I muſt confeſs) is got in me from this Text, that if a Miniſter have a call (with a good conſcience) to a new place, or new work, though it be not neceſſary, it is lawful for him to have a <hi>particular</hi> Ordination to the ſame; and I think that the hands of a grave Biſhop, and good men, laid on him afreſh, with their Faſting and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Prayers for Gods bleſſing upon him in it, were like to do him no harm.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49405:7"/>
            <p>But to come to the bottom, To judge aright of Re-ordination, we muſt firſt conſider what is Ordination. <hi>Ordinatio</hi> (ſay Proteſtant Divines) is <hi>vocationis confirmatio.</hi> The <hi>Leyden</hi> Divines, drop this definition. <hi>Ordinandi poteſtas, ſeu in Miniſterio confirmandi, &amp;c.</hi> Diſp. 42. Theſ. 37. <hi>Ordinatio</hi> (ſayes <hi>Ameſius</hi>) <hi>nihil aliud eſt quam ſolennis declaratio, ut coronatio Regis, aut inauguratio Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratûs.</hi> De conſc. l. 4. c. 25. Some of our eminent Divines being conſulted, do ſay, (I am told) Ordination is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Approbation,</hi> a publick ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving a man as fit to be a Miniſter; I would expreſs it thus, <hi>A ſolemn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of his Call.</hi> I take theſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions in effect to be the ſame; If they differ, I rather chooſe the firſt, both as moſt comprehenſive of the other, and alſo as moſt received; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as <hi>Wollebius</hi> going about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine Ordination, gives it no other name: <hi>Confirmatio</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>eſt perſonae ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae introductio, in quâ, publicis precibus praemiſsis, Eccleſiae comendatur, ei<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49405:7"/>vocatio, impoſitis manibus confirmatur.</hi> From which hint I will recall that place which is to be more then once made uſe of, as the cleareſt Text we have about this ſolemnity, to wit, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and called by the Holy Ghoſt to their work, St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, Certain Teachers who were there, <hi>prayed and faſted, and layed their hands on them</hi> (that is, ordained them) and ſent them away; and then in the two next Chapters going on, and declaring their journeys and acts, when they had done thus (ſays he) they returned to <hi>Antioch, from whence they had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the grace of God, for the work which they fulfilled,</hi> in which words he does plainly ſeem to deſcribe that matter, in the former narration. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination then is, out of doubt, (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be beſides) a ſolemn recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending (the word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti</hi>) or committing of a perſon to the grace of God, for the work unto which he is called. Unto this, let me yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49405:8"/>add the fore-cited Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> again more at large. <hi>Vocationis eſſentia eſt in electione Eccleſiae &amp; acceptatione electi. Adjunctum conſequens &amp; conſummans eſt Ordinatio, quae nihil aliud est quam ſolennis quaedam introductio Miniſtri jam electi in ipſius functionis liberam functionem.</hi> Medul. Theol. l. 1. c. 39. One thing only I muſt not let paſs, as ſome <hi>light</hi> in the way here, and to our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; that when ſuch Divines as theſe, do ſay, that Ordination is nothing elſe, but a Declaration, Approbation, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of our Calling: Do you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, it not directly of our <hi>call by man,</hi> (where lyes alone, I think, the ſhortneſs of their ſight) but of our <hi>call by God,</hi> and then it is exceeding well. You will, ſomewhere, when I ſhall ſpeak of this farther after, ſee the clearneſs and conſequence hereof. Now thoſe men who have imbibed ſuch a notion only of Ordination, as thus defined, will I ſuppoſe ſoon conclude that a double Approbation, Declaration, or Confirmation of the ſame Miniſtry is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49405:8"/>no ſuch matter but the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of it may be reſolved when but once the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedience</hi> is cleer.</p>
            <p>I deny not but there is more in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation then this, which creates the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, to wit, that it it gives the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall function; yet will I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede it, but ſuppoſe it, and go on (though we have a cleer inſtance flat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, (in <hi>Paul</hi>) when again we come to it,) upon that ſuppoſition; It ſuffices us if in <hi>re-ordination</hi> there be no more, and ſo much; for it is about that, our queſtion lyes. And I know, it is the generall ſentiments of mens ſpirits muſt taſt the thing at laſt, and determine it for us, whether good or bad (which will therefore be proper for a Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſome receiving it in their firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions as a ſecond <hi>baptiſm,</hi> others only, as another <hi>marrying</hi> when the firſt is good before in the ſight of God, but queſtionable in Law, and made ſure. And ſo I remember a worthy Doctor I ſpoke with occaſionally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, did expreſſe it by Uſury, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49405:9"/>in the common opinion is evill as to thoſe that require it, but not unlawfull, as to thoſe that upon their neceſſity do give it. <hi>In adiaphoris</hi> (ſaies <hi>Gerſon</hi>) <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioris judicio maxime credendum, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam ille vice Dei tibi dicet, quid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit et quid decet. De. Relig. perf. part,</hi> 3.</p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49405:9"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>HAving in my firſt paper made theſe ſcatter'd efforts already, I ſhall now more roundly and freely lay you down my opinion, with a larger compaſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole matter in five or ſix pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. For the doing whereof [wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the way that touchy objection of the Covenant, which for my oaths ſake at my Degrees in the univerſity I never took, and if it were to do again could not take] I need not any elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diſquiſition, which neither the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a letter, or my time, or my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtock can allow; but I ſhall ſet my thoughts down faithfully as they fall into my pen, travailing only with words, (as already I have done) to deliver my mind, and not with the lick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the expreſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I doubt not of <hi>Preſbyterial</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but that thoſe men who have been ordained without a Biſhop, have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49405:10"/>done, and do well, but according to their office and duty, in adminiſtring the word and ſacraments as miniſters of Chriſt and ſtewards of the myſteries of God. I can as well doubt, whether my people before me are men or living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not wheels or ſome things moved only by weights and engines; as I can doubt of this. The judgment of Biſhop <hi>Uſher, Downam, Carleton,</hi> Archdeacon <hi>Maſon, Field</hi> of the Church. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 39. and the practiſe of the Reformed Churches, is known in the caſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It appears in the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> was all one by theſe Texts. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. with 7. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17. with 28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2. This, Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> thought ſafeſt to own. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Apoſtles, and conſequently while there was Apoſtles there was no <hi>Biſhops.</hi> I ſpeak here but after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent judgment of our late King. The Churches then had recourſe unto them (as might be prooved by their ſending
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49405:10"/>ſtill to <hi>Paul</hi> about their affairs, in many places) which makes, and anſwers I think for Epiſcopacy; They had then no <hi>Biſhops</hi> indeed, becauſe the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts filled up the uſe of them. Whether the miniſters at firſt were all <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> and for avoyding of ſchiſm and faction, they choſe out one to be <hi>Biſhop</hi> (as <hi>Jerome:</hi>) Or whether at firſt they were all <hi>Biſhops</hi> and as their <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories</hi> encreaſed, and the people came in, they ordained <hi>Preſbyters</hi> under them, I leave to the ſeverall palates of the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious. This I take to be certain: while the work was not divided, they muſt needs be both but the ſame office, unto which either name was common; but when the work was divided, then they diſtinguiſhed the names and kept them up accordingly. See the Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Morice</hi> his moſt candid, cleer, and impartiall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the whole matter of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and both compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in his excellently learned book the ſecond Edition in Folio from <hi>p.</hi> 146 to 169.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49405:11"/>
               <p n="3">3. Whenſoever the diſtinction aroſe, I believe, that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> are not different <hi>orders</hi> of the Miniſtry, as a Prieſt and a Deacon is; but only the one is the ſame office with the other in a different <hi>degree</hi> of eminency. See the 42 queſt. in <hi>Biſhop Davenants</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. The Apoſtle in his firſt Epiſtle ſaies, <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained with the laying on of the hands of the <hi>Preſbytery:</hi> In the ſecond, by the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of his hands; You may gather from hence that <hi>Paul</hi> muſt needs be then one of the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> and ordained as one of them (the agent muſt act <hi>quá tale</hi> to the production of the effect; I ſpeak this <hi>ad hominem</hi>) and conſequently that <hi>Preſbyterial</hi> ordination and <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> is the ſame; So that the old rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <hi>Magis &amp; minus non variant ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em</hi> does ſatisfie me here; though I forget not (if I could believe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle indeed to be ſo criticall) an acute annotation of my own grave and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Biſhop (in his diſcourſe with mee) upon the two Prepoſitions, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49405:11"/>the one place imports authority, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſſiſtance only in the other. And yet, what if there be here it ſelf ſome double kind of Ordination, which for ought any one can be ſure of, was ſo: though you and I put not our beliefe to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas a moſt Reverend, late, and moderate Prelate is noted to have ſtated the matter thus, that <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial</hi> Ordination is valid, but <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical:</hi> Let it be underſtood only, where the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> government is in force; If a man ſhould, now <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is up, go to be ordained only by <hi>Preſbyters;</hi> no doubt but this, in every true <hi>Epiſcopal Judgment,</hi> is <hi>Schiſm:</hi> but, when the Biſhops were down here, and in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, where there are no Biſhops, it is rather queſtionable, to my thinking, whether it were not tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe of ſpirit, not to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Ordination which is going, and preſent neceſſity puts upon him. <hi>Si Orthodoxi Presbyteri, ne pereat Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, alios Presbyteros cogantur Ordinare;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49405:12"/>Ego non auſim hujuſmodi Ordinationes pronunciare irritas,</hi> ſayes <hi>Davenant,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoted. See the ſecond part of <hi>Jus Divinum Miniſterii Evangelici,</hi> where Ordination by <hi>Presbyters</hi> is juſtified at large, and more large than I need here mention.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I will diſtinguiſh then between what Ordination is required to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a part a man to the Office of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the ſight of God, and what is requiſite to the making him received as a Miniſter among men, and give him authority (or full repute) to execute that Office in the Church or place where he ſhall be called: I believe (as before) that Ordination by the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery only (ſufficing but a little while ago to both) ſuffices ſtill to the former, (ſuppoſing Ordination goes ſo far). But we all begin to know alſo, that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination now by a Biſhop, is neceſſary to the latter; and, conſequently, though I have been ordained before by the Presbytery, this hinders not, but I may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49405:12"/>be ordained again by the Biſhop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſeek not to be ordained by him to make me a Miniſter again, which I am <hi>in foro Dei</hi> already, but to have Authority (as to men) to uſe my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and be received as ſuch (which I cannot elſe) <hi>in foro Eccleſiae Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae.</hi> And this, me thinks, I am a little juſtified in, that when I was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the Presbytery, the very words uſed at the point, (to my beſt memory) were, <hi>Whom by the laying on of hands, we ſet a part for the Office of the Miniſtry,</hi> and in the Ordination by the Biſhop, they are, <hi>Take authority to Preach the Word and Miniſter the Sacraments in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where thou ſhalt be appointed,</hi> that is, in thy place. Not, but thoſe words do confer both of theſe (ſuppoſing what is ſuppoſed) to the unordained before; yet does not that hinder, but rather argue, If they do confer both to others, they may doubtleſs (and actually do) confer one (and can but the one only) to ſuch as are in my caſe: In ſhort, there is my Miniſtry, and the uſe of
<pb n="02" facs="tcp:49405:13"/>my Miniſtery in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church: My firſt Ordination (as we ſuppoſe) hath given me the one, yet is the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not ſuperfluous, becauſe it conduces (and that legally or <hi>regularly</hi>) to the other. I mean clearly, as to authority, freedom at leaſt, and reception in the ſame.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whereas the Scripture is clear about ſubjection to Superiours, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical; <hi>Obey thoſe that are over you in the Lord. Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake:</hi> I do queſtion, whether eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that yields to Epiſcopacy in his judgement (if but only as not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, and humane Inſtitution) is not obliged hereunto, if it may be had on this account, without reclaiming, or prejudice to his former Miniſtry. I ſay not barely, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears a thing <hi>lawful,</hi> while we ſee how it may done, but being ſtood upon, a <hi>due,</hi> to be done; and if any thing be amiſs, it is in them that exact it, and not in us that cannot help it. For what is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49405:13"/>Re-ordination in this caſe, but a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the order of that Church-Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is again ſet over us? And what evil is there more in it, then a ſecond marrying (as before) or confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (with a new) my former title to my living? If it be required of me, Why may I not be ordained twice as well as once, and thrice as well as twice, if there be ſtill reaſon ſufficient for it? May not the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy be repeated, and yet Gods Name not be taken in vain by it? Is it enough to make our Liturgy unlawful, becauſe we have, in one Service, the Lords Prayer twice over? I confeſs, I read indeed of one <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in Scripture, and a ſtreſs is laid upon it, but I read not ſo of <hi>one</hi> Ordination. Where there is <hi>no law</hi> to the contrary; where I pray lyes the <hi>tranſgreſsion?</hi> It is true, there may be found in ſome anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Canons ſomething againſt this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, where they had not the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Si quis Epiſcopus, aut Presbyter, aut Diaconus ſecundam ab aliquo Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem
<pb n="02" facs="tcp:49405:14"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49405:14"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49405:15"/>ſuſceperit, deponitor, tam ipſe quàm qui ipſum ordinavit,</hi> ſay the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal Canons of the Apoſtles. <hi>Can.</hi> 67. Where this very diſtinction thus made of the Clergy, does witneſs them (this one of them, at leaſt) to be of after-times, and ſo forged, as <hi>Rivet</hi> notes it. I know alſo the <hi>Trent</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, out of the Schoolmen, do tell me (with an <hi>Anathema</hi>) that there is an indelible character imprinted by three of their Sacraments (whereof this is one) for which cauſe, they cannot be iterated: but I know not, that any of them can tell, what this character is, or where, or how it is impreſſed, or ſhew it me in the Bible, or in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or that the Proteſtants do make any thing at all of it. <hi>Synopſ. pur. Theol. Diſp,</hi> 43. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 36. Let my fear, O Lord, be taught me by thy Precepts, and neither by mans meer notions, nor Tradition. <hi>Quod Baptiſmus non ſit ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus</hi> (ſayes <hi>Chemnitius</hi> in his <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men de Charactere) de re magná agitur. Pactum gratiae in illo Deus nobiſcune
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49405:15"/>iniit. — Illud verò</hi> (ſayes he, blaming the <hi>Trent</hi> determination) <hi>quod Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi proprium eſt, ut ſcilicet non ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, ad ſuos Ordines tranſtulerunt.</hi> You may ſee eaſily through this little cranny, the true light of this Great Mans free thoughts. Will you be pleaſed therefore to hear an honeſt, learned and impartial Doctor, ſpeaking his mind out full for him. Dr. <hi>Baldwin,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of <hi>Wittenberg. De caſibus conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae,</hi> putting this very caſe, Whether a man ordained by the Papiſts, may be ordained again by us, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, that there is no neceſſity of it, does yet clearly deliver here, his thoughts in this matter. <hi>Quod ſi</hi> quis <hi>exiſtimat ſe tranquilliùs ſuo in noſtris Eccleſiis Officio, perfungi poſſe, ſi etiam noſtris ritibus ad Sacroſanctum Miniſterium utatur, nihil obſtat, quin Ordinationem à noſtris acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere poſsit: non enim eadem eſt ratio Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationis, quae Baptiſmi, qui iterari non poteſt; Hoc enim Sacramentum eſt Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, illa autem externus tantum ritus.</hi> Lib. 4. c. 6. caſ. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49405:16"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>I Have done now with my Eſſay as to the Queſtion. I come to the Scruples and Objections that have run into my Soul like water. I ſhall endeavour through Divine Aſſiſtance, to lave them out as well as I can, by Confeſſion, or Solution.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, it hath been this: The Apoſtle limiting the uſe of our Chriſtian liberty in indifferent things to the rule of charity, inſtances in meats offered to Idols. The weak Brethren thought in their conſciences it unlawful, to eat of ſuch meats; the ſtronger Chriſtian hereupon is bound to forbear, becauſe they ſeeing him who had knowledge ſit at meat, their conſciences would be emboldned to eat likewiſe, who having not that knowledge, ſhould ſin. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the caſe here. Many of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren do think it unlawful (it is likely) to be ordained again; Now they ſeeing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49405:16"/>me, though the meaneſt among them, yet whom they think may have ſome knowledge, to be re-ordained: Shall they not be emboldned to do ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which if they do, whilſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (or doubt) it to be unlawful, they <hi>periſh. But when you ſin againſt the Brethren, and wound their weak conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, you ſin againſt Chriſt.</hi> I confeſs, I do the rather propoſe this, for the ſeeking ſatisfaction, if it can be given me, in regard of the vaſt range the Caſe hath, and takes in more eſpecially all Ceremony; I cannot wear a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, nor read Common Prayer, (at this interim) or ſtand up at the Creed: Nay, I cannot wear my hair long, and a hundred more, certainly, indifferent things; but ſome do think theſe in their conſciences unlawful; and ſo, while I embolden them by my pattern to do the ſame, I occaſion their ruine, and incur the hazard of ſuch Texts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14, 15, 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11, 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6, 7.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49405:17"/>
               <p>I muſt profeſs, if this Propoſition will ariſe from any one, or from all theſe Texts, that a man who is ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a thing as indifferent and lawful, muſt yet forbear upon the account, that by his example, others may be embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſame, who having not that knowledge, do judge it unlawful, and ſo ſin if they do it; then is the way of poor Chriſtians (the Lord knows) very ſtraight: Nevertheleſs (beſides the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hammonds</hi> interpretation of that Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. bearing away quite the edge of that place) I am though, through grace, ſomething enlightned to judge, that a man may ſometimes do much good in leading an example to the doubtful, when a thing is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming neceſſary, as he may do much amiſs in things more certainly lawful, that are better ſpared. As for the Schools definition of Scandal; I ſay, an indifferent commanded, becomes <hi>rectum,</hi> which was <hi>minùs rectum</hi> before; and <hi>Scandalum</hi> with them is, <hi>Dictum vel factum</hi> minus rectum <hi>praebens alteri oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionem
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49405:17"/>ruinae.</hi> I will take up with that here of Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> treating about in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things in this caſe, and menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning <hi>Pauls</hi> circumciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> and yet not <hi>Titus,</hi> as to the point. <hi>Nihil jam</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>hâc regulâ expeditius, quàm Utendum libertate noſtrâ ſi in proximi noſtri aedificationem cedat; ſin ita proximo non expediat, eâ tunc abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum.</hi> Inſt. lib. 3. c. 19. §. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49405:18"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>THE grand Objection in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place and chief that I can think of; and which, I am perſwaded, if I can ſatisfie thoroughly, I have done my work; I will lay down as cleer as poſſibly I can frame it: for it hath come in often, and laid long with the dint of it in my thoughts. Ordination is that which according to Divines does give a man the office of the Miniſtery (they mean, they ſay, <hi>as to the Eſſence of the outward Call, Jus Divin. Evan.</hi> ch. 11.) This is the end they account here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Now when a man is a Miniſter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, there is not this end; If there be not it's end, it is to no purpoſe, an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, or Gods name, taken in vain which is againſt the Third Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, as cleerly, I hope, directly, and fully; and ſhall enlarge upon it after. There are more ends
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49405:18"/>then one in Ordination, as in Baptiſm and other Inſtitutions; It is not neceſſary to the taking or uſing an ordinance that a man be capable of all it's ends (I might adde, if need were, nor the grand end) ſo long as there is ſome right and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient end of the ſame. <hi>Ordination</hi> (it is ſaid) <hi>does not inſtall a man in his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but gives a man his commiſsion and authority,</hi> that is, it muſt be meant, does not only doe this; for it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily does the firſt, whether it does the laſt or not. I will ſuppoſe then, it does no leſſe. It makes a man a Miniſter (I ſay I ſuppoſe this, not grant it) and alſo ſignifies him to be ſuch before men. It gives the office and alſo it makes a man to be <hi>received as ſuch</hi> in the Church where he is ſent, which is a matter of great weight and open importance, as I ſhall ſay more about it. Now I am fixed here; Though we that are Miniſters already, cannot be ordained to the one end, which is ſuppoſed the moſt common (our caſe being peculiar); yet are we, may we, and, for any thing I know (if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49405:19"/>required) ought we to be ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for the other. The common and generall end of Baptiſm was for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, yet was Jeſus Chriſt bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, who was not capable of that end (but ſome others). The common end of Ordination is for the office (as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed); yet if the Biſhop ſhall ſay here, <hi>Why comeſt thou</hi> to be ordained? <hi>Thou haſt no need</hi> that art a Miniſter already. I will anſwer him humbly in my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours words, <hi>Suffer it ſo to be now for it becommeth us to fulfill all righteouſneſs,</hi> It becometh us to conform to the peace uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and government of the Church, as well as State (ſo far as we can) in the Nation.</p>
               <p>St <hi>Paul</hi> is <hi>made a Miniſter</hi> by Chriſt himſelf; Mark the words well, for they are beyond diſpute, <hi>I have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thee for this purpoſe to make thee a Miniſter. And now I ſend thee to the Gentiles to open their blind eys,</hi> &amp;c. Act. 26.16, 17, 18. And yet is he ordained after by the hands of men, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.3. Will any man ſay that the impoſition of hands did make him a Miniſter, or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49405:19"/>confer his office? That were not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that text, but ſuch a manifeſt wrong he will never put up, who in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes ſtands upon it, that he was an Apoſtle, <hi>not of men, neither by man, but by</hi> Chriſt <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. which is the truth. 'Tis plain then, that a man who is a Miniſter already, may be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; or that it is not neceſſary to be ordained only to this end, to have the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice conferred on him. And now then my Friend that art in my caſe, doe thou tell the Biſhop, thou art a Miniſter already; Be ſure thou doeſt not renounce thy former ordination, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as much as in thee lyes) all thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall acts paſt (together with thy conſent to the Reformed Churches) for any thing; If he ſhall thereupon ask thee, wherefore then wilt thou be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained? Say, To this end, this very end, St. <hi>Paul</hi> here was ordained, let it be what it will, it is that alone I come for; which indeed in effect is nothing elſe but the canonicall ſtamp of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of thy former
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49405:20"/>vocation; and as for the bare Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it ſelf twice uſing, which alone is left to be excepted at, value it not. Who does not know that impoſition of hands with prayer is uſed for Confirmation, as well as Ordination?</p>
               <p>I will advance here on further; The reaſon of a precept is to be look't on as the precept; To perform a precept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reaſon of it, is to break it; To do according to the reaſon, though not according to the precept, is to keep it; We have no precept in Scripture for Re-ordination; but we have here, in this inſtance, <hi>the reaſon of it.</hi> Let any one tell me the reaſon of this impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands upon <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Lucius</hi> and <hi>Niger,</hi> who could not be made a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>by man</hi> ſeeing Chriſt had appeared to him (as is ſaid) <hi>for that purpoſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; &amp; I will preſume to give the ſame or the like, for our re-ordination by the Biſhop. If you ſay, Here was a command of the Holy Ghoſt. It is true: but that takes not away the reaſon of the rite; the thing muſt have it's due end, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49405:20"/>reaſon, but the rather, for that.</p>
               <p>What then is the reaſon indeed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? Is it for to give the miniſterial of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and nothing elſe? Surely if it does that at all (which one may think God alone does by the warrant of his word upon his enabling gift, and the mans Conſent); Yet is not this the reaſon alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for certain, becauſe here is an inſtance to the contrary, let any man cavill at it what he can. What is the reaſon then? Why, really, I think it is this. This ſolemn rite does give the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant repute, or valuation, to a man of a Miniſter; ſo that he who was truly called of God before, is now <hi>received as ſuch,</hi> by all, as to the exerciſe of his function with freedome and acceptation; And this is that authority alone I count the Biſhop gives (at leaſt as to us) in thoſe words, <hi>Take thou authority</hi> &amp;c. To wit an authority of <hi>eſteem</hi> in regard of men, who many will not, and many perhaps out of conſcience miſlead, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, hold me for a true, or <hi>legall</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter otherwiſe? And hereupon you ſee,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49405:21"/>upon what ground it is we go in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination) and that is no other, then the very reaſon it ſelf of Ordination; which, believe it, is not a little matter, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no leſſe then that of the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, namely, the very <hi>courſe and glorifying</hi> of our Goſpell, which ought to be, I think, one of the greateſt Concernments to us in the world.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort then, for we are now at the bottome; Forasmuch as our former ordination by the <hi>Presbytery</hi> though it be good according to God, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſuch as <hi>ought</hi> to give us this reputation (or outward authority) as Miniſters (which is the reaſon of ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) yet <hi>does</hi> not do it and reach it's end, in our Church, by reaſon of the times (and perhaps according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Laws) as they are now changed, and like to ſtand: I argue, where the reaſon of the precept is repeated, who can deny, nay who dare refuſe, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of the duty?</p>
               <p>And here the prime knot of the whole
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49405:21"/>difficulty is alſo looſed, which is this. We on one hand dare not but own out former Ordination as valid for our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall acts paſt: On the other hand, if we owne the firſt as valid, what room can there be for a ſecond? There muſt be ſome ſenſe therefore, wherein it is to be conceived not valid, null, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as the caſe truly is) <hi>nullified</hi> (as to ſome conſiderable intents) or elſe a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ordination does nothing but what is done, which is abſurd. I anſwer therefore directly. The validity of our former Ordination <hi>accipitur dupliciter.</hi> This is what is cleer, and ſo may ſeem eaſy to you, found; but coſt mee many thoughts to frame and find. This va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity I ſay, is to be taken either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what it <hi>ought</hi> to do; or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of what it <hi>does</hi> do, as I have ſaid; It would be fuller, if I could ſay, In regard of what it ought to doe according to the Law of God; and in regard of what it does do, according to the law of our Church or Land: wherein I am not ſo well-skill'd, as to ſpeak ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49405:22"/>In the firſt regard, (to wit, of what it <hi>ought</hi> to do) we ſtand upon it, to be valid or good; we profeſs that, that alone is ſuch, according to Scripture, as <hi>ought</hi> to give us the repute and full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception as Miniſters, by all perſons, and to all intents and purpoſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: But in the ſecond regard, (to wit, of what it <hi>does</hi> do) we yield it is not valid, we acknowledge it indeed, hereby (not to be ſo); It <hi>does</hi> not do this, 'tis true; it is that we perceive, and know, and complain of: what through error in ſome, and wilfulneſs and injury in others, they render it to us as null (both as to the main, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial effects) ſo that it will not any longer ſerve the turn, or end (through the ſtream of the times, how happy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever otherwiſe) to give our Miniſtry its free courſe (the marrow of all); and upon that account, are we ordained again. Which being, I ſay, the reaſon (or one main reaſon, at leaſt) of this rite it ſelf, it is ſubſtantially ſatisfactory (and I ſuſpect, alſo obligatory) for our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49405:22"/>yielding to the ſame. And thus do I avoid both the ſin on one hand, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning our <hi>firſt</hi> Orders; and the Soloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm on the other, of doing only what is done in our <hi>laſt.</hi> When yet I ſhould have thought this matter might have paſſed pretty well at firſt, if it had been but ſo determined, as to be (if men would) ſome kind of Soloeciſm, but no ſin.</p>
               <p>You have the body of this main Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; I ſhall now proceed to the limbs of ſome farther ſcruples.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ordination is our entrance into the Miniſtry; How can a man have a double entrance into the ſame ſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Beſides that this is taken off, in the reaſon of the thing (as to its foundation) I return; So is Marriage, an entrance into the conjugal eſtate. Suppoſe a couple marryed only by the Magiſtrate, and as to ſome conſiderable effect, their marriage is in queſtion, Who would doubt, but upon ſuch, or any other ſerious cauſe for it, they may be marryed again by the Book of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49405:23"/>Common Prayer? And why not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this very reaſon? Becauſe, there is nothing elſe in it, but only, that that Form which is compiled in the Book, for the entring, or (what is the truth) ſignifying the entrance of two perſons into wedlock, is now uſed, to ſignifie theſe to be entred, or confirming them legally in that eſtate, which it will do as well, as enter them at firſt? Who will ſay, it is a ſin, or tranſgreſſion, to uſe it ſo? A great piece of matter, and miſ-uſage, is it not? Apply the ſame here, and if any will condemn us for the like uſe of the form of ordering Prieſts, let them include the multitudes, that have been ſo marryed in theſe times, and take heed, they can anſwer it before the Lord. <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt thy Brother?</hi> Rom. 14.10. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignum eſt</hi> (ſayes the Father) <hi>ut prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ea qua nos Deo, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> digniores ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> indigniores poſſunt facere, alii alios vel condemnemus, vel judicemus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ordination is not a naked ſign, only to declare a man a Miniſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49405:23"/>men; but there is grace implored; we are recommended to Gods grace, and we are to ſuppoſe grace accompanying of it; Now, Is not the being twice ordained, a kind of offering an indignity to the grace of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If we look into 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. we have footing for a diſtinction of Grace; <hi>I laboured, yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> There is therefore the grace of God <hi>in us;</hi> or, <hi>with us;</hi> That grace which is implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, unto which we are committed, and may expect from this ſolemnity, is, I take it, the grace of God <hi>with us,</hi> the aſſiſtance and bleſſing of God upon us for our work; which being what we may alwayes pray for, or what is continually vouchſafed; I hope there is no more evil here, then the bidding ſeveral times, <hi>God ſpeed,</hi> or, <hi>bleſsing</hi> our friends <hi>in the Name of the Lord</hi> more then once. It was no wayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory to the divinity of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> firſt Dream, that it was ſeconded by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>For that the dream was doubled
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49405:24"/>unto</hi> Pharaoh <hi>twice, it is, becauſe the thing is eſtabliſhed by God.</hi> By the way, A ſecond Ordination then, by various perſons and rites, deſtroyes not the firſt, but is an <hi>Eſtabliſhment;</hi> the title by which I have choſen to call it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>But there is a gift given by Ordination, which is in us. Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.14. with 2 Tim. 1.6. <hi>And that gift, it is likely, can be received but once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> It is probable, that this gift was ſomething extraordinary, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to <hi>Timothy.</hi> Becauſe; 1. It was given him by this ceremony (as is thought) according to the miraculous gifts, of thoſe times. 2. He was an extraordinary Officer, an Evangeliſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. or at leaſt, a ſingular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. 3. It is given him by Oracle. 4. There is no mention of ſuch a gift, in the Ordination of any other. If ſo, this objection is quite taken off from us: If not, but the Gift is ordinary, it will
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49405:24"/>concern us; And what then is it (let us ſearch) that is conferred by this Rite?</p>
               <p>It is not the grace of God <hi>(gratum faciens)</hi> or ſaving grace; for that is not tyed to this means. Nor is it the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal talent, Endowment, Parts, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities for the Miniſtry; for thoſe are tryed, and to be found firſt in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be ordained, and therefore not given hereby. Nor ſhould it be the Office it ſelf (one may judge) becauſe 1. What need is there, the word <hi>Gift</hi> ſhould be taken Metonymically, when it may be taken properly? 2. How can the Office be ſaid, to be ſtirr'd up (<hi>Stir up the gift that is in thee,</hi> ſayes the ſecond Text) which is proper of the grace to diſcharge it? 3. That which is yet harſher, How can it be ſaid of the Office, The Gift that is <hi>in thee?</hi> It is proper to ſay, a man is <hi>in his Office;</hi> but to ſay, a man; Office is <hi>in him,</hi> ſeems ſtrange. 4. If it be thought, the office muſt neceſſarily be conferred by this rite, it is falſe; in our
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49405:25"/>inſtance of <hi>Paul</hi> for certain, and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> likely. <hi>Haec manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m impoſitto non eò ſpectabat ut Epiſcopalem gratiam cis largiretur; ſed (docente Scripturâ) ut ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregarentur in opus, &amp; commendarentur gratiae Dei,</hi> Maſon. de Min. Ang. p. 46. If it be thought, it may and does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, where it is not before, that ſhall be ſtill ſuppoſed by me, though not granted, nor conceived.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe it then, ſeeing it is the moſt currant ſenſe, that by this gift is meant <hi>Docendi Officium,</hi> as our <hi>London</hi> Divines, with <hi>Anſelm, Thomas, Cajetane, Gerſon, Bucer;</hi> or, what is all one, Authority, Power, and Commiſſion for this Office and work, as our Book of Orders, <hi>Take thou authority to Preach the Word, and Miniſter the Sacraments. Ordo, eſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum quoddam, quo ſpiritualis poteſtas traditur Ordinato &amp; Officium,</hi> ſayes <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard.</hi> Now then, the queſtion will be this only, at the higheſt, Whether an Authority or Commiſſion to an Office or work, in the nature of the thing, may be renewed and refreſhed? And there
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49405:25"/>is one inſtance alone to this point, may I think, pluck the ſuperſtitious doubt up by the root from the heart. It is this; The Apoſtles beyond queſtion, had Miſſion, and Commiſſion, and ſo this <hi>gift,</hi> (whatſoever it is) from Chriſt, when he made their Miniſters in his life: and yet we find them Commiſſion, or Authority miniſterial renewed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly again after Chriſts Reſurrection. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22, 23. Which herein hath the more ſupport in it, <hi>(modo liceat)</hi> that it is the ſame form which is uſed to us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>repetition.</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Text, underſtands by this Gift only, that, through the Prayers of the Church, Grace (to wit, <hi>gratis data</hi>) is impetrated on the ordained: and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Timothy, Certum eſt, &amp; doctrinà</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>&amp; aliis dotibus priù eum excelluiſſe.</hi> And ſo, I hope, there is no ſcruple, how more talents, and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtill from God may be repeated and freſh ſought. I will lean upon the inſtance mentioned, and ſuppoſe you can hardly raiſe an Objection, intrinſecal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49405:26"/>to the thing, but <hi>that</hi> may be turned ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially to it.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid, <hi>The Apoſtles were ſent only before to the</hi> Jews; <hi>now they are ſent to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and ſo there is need of a new Commiſsion (for a new, it ſeems to be by the word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Mat. 16.19. <hi>in the future tenſe, pointing to the time in</hi> John). I return then, There is the <hi>office</hi> of the Apoſtleſhip, and the <hi>uſe</hi> of that Office in a farther place, (even unto all Nations). Though they had Commiſſion already belike for the one, this does not hinder, but they may have a new (or renewed) for the other. So ſtate I the Re-ordaineds caſe: They are Miniſters already; but for the uſe of their Miniſtry, as to the place, or farther ſervice, whereunto they ſhall be called, Who ſhall forbid the like to them? If you ſcruple here, I have no new work, or new place: Yet you may re-mind our inſtance of <hi>Paul</hi> before, who was ſent by Chriſt at firſt to the Gentiles at large, and yet is ordained again after, and ſent to the <hi>ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49405:26"/>
               <p>Let this <hi>dilemma,</hi> at leaſt ſerve thy turn; If thou keepeſt thy place, and thy conſcience here is <hi>weak,</hi> the Act for <hi>Confirmation of Miniſters,</hi> ſecures thee upon thy Ordination thou haſt: If thou art turn'd out, or haſt a ſafe Call by Providence to a new place, thou mayſt have a <hi>peculiar</hi> Ordination to that work. See beſides the former inſtance, <hi>Act.</hi> 11. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. and aſſure thy ſelf, it is light when the Sun is up. This were an account upon which the re-ordained haply, and re-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both, might be juſtified. And then, if, beſides an Ordination in <hi>general,</hi> to ſet apart a man for his Office, there may be a <hi>particular,</hi> to recommend him to the grace of God for his work in another place, Why may not this be diſtinguiſht upon need, as to the ſame place alſo? Thou muſt have, me thinks, but narrow thoughts of the Scripture, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it, if thou thinkeſt, that the continuance of thy Miniſtry, or the <hi>Parrheſia</hi> only, or full liberty thereof for the Lord, will not bear thee out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49405:27"/>for ſuch a matter. I chooſe for our ſelves the largeſt Foundation.</p>
               <p>Before I paſs hence, though, I cannot here but put a difference between the authority which Chriſt gave his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, whoſe Prerogative it is, to make his own Officers, and the authority man gives; As when it is ſaid, <hi>The Saints ſhall judge the world;</hi> Divines ſay, that is, by <hi>approving</hi> (as Aſſeſſors) Chriſts ſentence: So I take it, do men <hi>make Miniſters,</hi> by approving Chriſts call. There is then the ſpiritual inward pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and commiſſion for my office <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God.</hi> Ordination, I ſuppoſe, gives not this <hi>character;</hi> but it lies plainly, I judge, in theſe three things, Inſtitution, Ability, and Conſent: to wit, Chriſt hath appointed ſuch an Office to be; furniſhes a man with endowments for that Office; and gives him a <hi>will,</hi> ſo that he dedicates himſelf thereupon to that work. Here is Chriſts call. And what then doth man, but upon tryal, finding this ſo, he <hi>approves,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares</hi> him a Miniſter, by the ſolemnity
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49405:27"/>of Ordination, and ſo adds to him, an authority <hi>towards man,</hi> he had not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Let us know then, (and not be in the dark any longer); It is <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtill gives us our <hi>Office</hi> (thou muſt hold thy Office from him certainly, if thou art Chriſts Miniſter) and <hi>Man</hi> gives us <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</hi> Believe it, the Eſſence of this <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> authority, or <hi>call,</hi> which is all at laſt, that dare be aſſumed and aſcribed to Orders indeed (if men know once what it is) lies there: Ordination, for certain, is in its nature, a recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to the grace of God for our work, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. with chap. 14.26. And why might not any few good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or private Congregation (which were abſurd and inſolent) do this; but that this repute or valuation, to all intents, as Miniſters, is to be attained by that ſolemnity?</p>
               <p>And after this, I do begin to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, That this gift in <hi>Timothy,</hi> (though there be ſomething elſe yet hangs in my mind) is indeed, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of his Office, (eſpecially ſeeing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49405:28"/>this is the ſenſe, you may think, moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to me) which will appear mainly by that Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. <hi>This charge I commit to thee ſon</hi> Timothy, <hi>according to the propheſies which went before on thee, that thou by them mightest war a good warfare.</hi> This warfare (compare it with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.) is his Miniſtry. Hence I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, (I can't ſay ſurely) what was given <hi>Timothy</hi> by Propheſie, was his Miniſtry. But this <hi>gift,</hi> is that, which was <hi>given</hi> him by <hi>Propheſie.</hi> Therefore, this <hi>gift</hi> is his Miniſtry. Well now, upon this ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you ſee, how <hi>Timothy</hi>'s Miniſtry, or Office is given him: The objected Text ſayes expreſly, <hi>by Propheſie.</hi> What that means, the other Text doth illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, to wit, by Revelation; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then when the Holy Ghoſt bid, <hi>Separate me</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas, in the <hi>Acts.</hi> If God, then by expreſs call, <hi>gives</hi> him his Office, when it is added, <hi>With the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> it can be only as in the parallel inſtance, by the way of a declarative aſſent, allowance, or confirmation.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49405:28"/>
               <p>And now, I hope, the vizard of this uncouth thing, <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> does fall off: For is it indeed ſo againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and all example? Is it ſuch a Gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, to be re-ordained, think you truly? What if I muſter upon you, now at laſt? The Apoſtles were re-ordained, <hi>Paul</hi> re-ordained, <hi>Barnabas</hi> re-ordained, and perhaps <hi>Timothy</hi> alſo. Let not your eyes, I pray, be holden, if it be ſo in good earneſt. <hi>Thoſe Divines</hi> (ſay the Provincial Aſſembly) <hi>define Ordination very well, that define it to be, Miſsio po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtativa.</hi> You ſee, I ſpeak not at the loweſt. Well then, The Apoſtles have one <hi>Authorative Miſsion,</hi> Mat. 10.7. and they have another alſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21. They are doubly ordained then, and both Ordinations extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. <hi>Paul</hi> hath <hi>Miſsion</hi> Poteſtative, from Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. And yet hath an open Ordination alſo by men, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. He is re-ordained, and one Ordination is extraordinary, and the other, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Barnabas</hi> hath Miſſion from the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 11.22. (and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49405:29"/>authoritative, no doubt) and another al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with <hi>Paul,</hi> by them at <hi>Antioch.</hi> Here is double Ordination, and both ordinary by men. I may ſtop here, for I have enough. Who will not be ready to ſay, Give me but one inſtance of this thing in Scripture, and I am ſatisfied? Loe here, is two or three for you: <hi>Nihil eſt tam certum, quàm quod ex dubio certum eſt.</hi> And yet, what if I add? The Biſhop hath no new order, or office from a Prieſt, and yet hath he a new Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without ſcruple. I will fold up this paper then with St. <hi>Cyprian. Non debemus attendere quid aliquis ante nos faciendum putaverit; ſed quid, qui ante omnes eſt, Chriſtus priùs fecerit: ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim hominis conſuetudinem ſequi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, ſed Dei veritatem.</hi> Lib. 2. Caecil. Epiſt. 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49405:29"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>A Third Objection, is this, <hi>To be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained, does ſeem, virtually to renounce our former Ordination: and for any to do ſo, (at leaſt, for me; after twelve years Miniſteral acts) were, I think, not only a light thing, but a heavy ſin: Beſides, it ſeems to be a kind of departure from our ſtation, and leaving the Presbytery, which makes a man look like one of the</hi> Lapſi, <hi>to ſome folks think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For anſwer to this; I do not know, what others may judge in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; but as for my ſelf, I am humbly perſwaded, That ſo long as a man doth clearly, and unfainedly, both before and after (unto the concern'd) as he hath occaſion, declare himſelf to the contrary, this <hi>will</hi> not by the Lord, and <hi>ought</hi> not by Man, to be laid to his charge; and that upon this evident rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Becauſe, Expreſſion in this caſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49405:30"/>does give Conſtruction to the Action. The denomination muſt be <hi>à fortiori;</hi> and there can be no doubt to the unbyaſſed; Whether a manifeſt declaration by mouth, or a dumb ſhew, or act, is the clearer (and ſo the ſtronger) ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: You may take one full inſtance, in the matter of the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> when they erected an Altar, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22. The body of <hi>Iſrael</hi> preſently riſe up, and look upon this as a renunciation of their Religion: Hereupon, they do but make direct profeſſion, That they had not <hi>built this Altar for Sacrifice, but for a witneſs,</hi> and you ſee preſently all are pacified; the Altar ſtands, and there is no more ſaid againſt it. Beſides, there is this here takes out the coar, that the thing is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally conceived (as if already they knew your mind) to be <hi>Neceſsity,</hi> Form, and <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> only, and no ſuch matter in the leaſt, as Renunciation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by it.</p>
               <p>Doubt. <hi>What if my Biſhop is of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That my former Ordination is null, and Ordains me in his mind only on that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49405:30"/>account; Will not that opinion of his, render me uncapable to be re-ordained by him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If, notwithſtanding his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he gives thee liberty to declare thy ſelf, there is no reaſon (thy conſcience being diſcharged) for thee, to imagine his opinion ſhould hinder thee herein any more, then the intention of the Prieſt in the matter of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But what ſhall I declare? That I come not for a new Ordination, but a legal confirmation of my former?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Of your former Call, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, if you will; The dream it ſelf of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> is not ſaid, to be confirmed by a ſecond; but the thing ſignified, was <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by <hi>both.</hi> For, to be a little accurate here; Though as to others, <hi>in ſenſu vulgari,</hi> (and to ſpeak only as a Divine) my former Ordination, may be ſaid hereby, to be confirmed, yet <hi>in ſenſu peculiari,</hi> as to the Biſhop himſelf, this opinion of his, makes it not properly a <hi>confirmation (Confirmare
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49405:31"/>eſt rem firmam facere;</hi> there muſt be <hi>res,</hi> before it be made firm, which he holds null) but his Act (as Lawyers ſpeak) works by way of <hi>Eſtoppel;</hi> ſo that he (nor any of his judgement) ſhall be able to implead my Miniſtry for the future:which is all one for the doing, and notrendring the thing vain, as if it were a confirmation in the moſt proper, and formal ſenſe in the world.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, as for my Call, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry it ſelf; in the very nature of the thing, it is hereby <hi>confirmed,</hi> ſo that, I have thereupon, the free uſe thereof in our Church, for which I come. Care not thou therefore for words, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy mind plainly, That Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Ordination is good in the ſight of God, as thou believeſt; that thou haſt not acted baſely without Orders hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and yet, in regard the times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, thou ſubmitteſt for the Goſpel ſake to theſe <hi>other</hi> alſo, that will paſs. This is enough: and then, I muſt tell thee, that the thing it ſelf is Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Ordination</hi> (I count) <hi>is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49405:31"/>of a mans call from Chriſt to the Miniſtry,</hi> (which is, his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>coram Deo) by the ſolemn</hi> God-ſpeed, <hi>allowance, or approbation of ſuch who are of authority, to give a man the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Miniſter</hi> (where lies <hi>poteſtas coram hominibus) to its due intents, in the Church where he is ſent.</hi> That I think, were a true, and almoſt full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition. And foraſmuch then, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the full current of the times, you ſee wherein you may look upon your <hi>firſt Orders,</hi> though true, to be null in certain reſpects, without ever the leſs eſteem of them indeed, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to them, and with the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans leave too, I trow; you have clear room and ground for ſubmiſſion to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination,</hi> as in the Paper before.</p>
               <p>And indeed, while thy Biſhop, and perhaps many other good men, and, it may be, ſome of the chief of thy own Pariſh are of this mind, That while thou haſt no other hands laid on thee, then ſuch of thy <hi>own degree,</hi> thou art not a Miniſter at all, or ſuch a one as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49405:32"/>thou oughteſt to be; and ſo perhaps they ſorrowfully, but ſilently get others to do ſome Miniſterial acts for them, and there grows ſtrangeneſs towards thee, and they greive for it; beſides the like and worſe effects: Who does not ſee here, That this thing is a matter of more conſequence, then thou couldſt at firſt think of: and if thereupon, thou yieldeſt to the remedy, thou doſt not go beyond (nor ſo far as) the Apoſtles own pattern, who became <hi>all things to all men,</hi> (as eſpecially in the caſe of <hi>Timothy</hi>) even to theſe ends only, the magnifying his Miniſtry, and that he might <hi>gain ſome;</hi> and who hath alſo left us a clear precept with his example, Rom. 15.2. <hi>Let every one of us pleaſe his neighbour for his edification.</hi> And here I may propoſe <hi>ex abundanti</hi> this farther, Whether an irrefragable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may not be drawn from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles uſe of Circumciſion upon any, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Reſurrection of Chriſt, to prove that an Ordinance may be uſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of the third Commandment,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49405:32"/>or other ſin, even then, when it cannot be directed to its principal, no, not its proper end; ſo long as it will but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one higher then all, to wit, The promotion of the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus?</p>
               <p>I will therefore now call the <hi>Reube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> inſtance again to mind, craving leave to make ſo much uſe thereof in the cloze, as humbly likewiſe (after this) to declare our caſe. There are many of us, who have been ſome years <hi>fellow Souldiers</hi> with our Brethren; we cannot find it in our hearts, to be lawful, to give our ſelves a <hi>diſcharge</hi> in this <hi>war,</hi> which were ſo pleaſing to the fleſh, upon a pretence that will not hold with the Lord; and hereupon we have been content to be farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, and ſubmit in this thing. Now the <hi>Lord God, the Lord God of Gods knows, we have not done this</hi> to erect an Altar againſt an Altar, one Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt another; we have not done it in <hi>rebellion,</hi> or renuntiation thereunto; but <hi>rather for fear of this thing, that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49405:33"/>in time to come</hi> (or that now is) they ſhould ſay, <hi>What have you to do with the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> or with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, that are not ordained according to the <hi>faſhion</hi> of the Land? and ſo they ſhall make us <hi>ceaſe</hi> from our ſervice of him; <hi>Therefore ſaid we, that it ſhall be when they ſhould ſay ſo to us, that we may ſay again, Behold the pattern,</hi> of your own orders <hi>for a witneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and you,</hi> that we have <hi>our part alſo in the Lord,</hi> and how much we deſire accommodation. And now, I hope, that <hi>Phineas</hi> himſelf, the High-Prieſt, and all our pious and tender Brethren, when they have heard theſe words, will be <hi>pleaſed,</hi> and let us paſs with that bleſſing; <hi>This day, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that God is among us, becauſe you have not committed this treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond part of the Objection. It hath pleaſed God, by his Providence, to call us univerſally to change, and it is not the intereſt now of good men to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49405:33"/>be ſtiffe, and dividing, but to be find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the moſt conſcionable grounds of complyance, as far as ever they can, with one another. It would have been ingenuous, I think, (for the caſe of <hi>Bancroft,</hi> and the <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbyters is known) if Epiſcopacy, would by ſome general act of Confirmation, have wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Ordination paſt; but, if ſhe deal, me thinks, (againſt her nature) Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, not generouſly, not Catholiquely herein, it will become us yet, (who are the parties thus ordained, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly concerned) to be fair. We know what is her chief flower; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be yielded to her, if we would have her part with any thing again; and ſo long as we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our own ſenſe, and eſcape the ſin, we are to comprimize the matter for our ſelves, by bringing our conſcience toward God, and ſubmiſſion to her, unto compoſition. If a ſecond Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, did neceſſarily, in the fact, imply a renunciation of the firſt; what a hainous thing had it been for <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49405:34"/>to be ordained after by men, that was <hi>made a Miniſter</hi> immediately by Chriſt? Aſſure your ſelf therefore, moſt firmly from the former Paper, about that matter.</p>
               <p>For my part, I will confeſs, although I am one that cannot be lookt on, as engaged to the Presbytery, any more then to have been ordained by them; yet am I ſo held under the convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the power and life of godlineſs in ſome of that ſort of men, above ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others; that I cannot let <hi>Naomi</hi> go eaſily, and much leſs, part with her with any indignity. When theſe good men (or party) were high, I could not fall in with them: Now they are down, my ſpirit, like <hi>Ruth,</hi> is more ready to cleave to them. Nevertheleſs, as for their way, and particular government, I cannot chooſe but retain my freedom, and be apt to underſtand with thoſe, that give us the greateſt latitude unto agreement and concord in the Nation, To which end, that tenent of <hi>Whitgift, (Def. Ad. p.</hi> 78, 83, 98.) to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49405:34"/>does conduce. <hi>It is true, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be tolerated in the Church as neceſſary to Salvation, or as an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, except it be contained in the Word of God. It is true alſo, That nothing in Ceremonies, Order, Diſcipline, or Government in the Church, is to be ſuffered, being againſt the Word. But that no Ceremony, Order, Diſcipline, or kind of Government, may be in the Church, except the ſame be expreſſed in the Word of God, is an abſurdity, and breedeth many inconveniences. For we know,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Calvin) that every Church hath liberty to ordain, and appoint ſuch a Form of Government as is apt and profitable for it, becauſe the Lord hath therein preſeribed no certainty:</hi> upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. as he quotes him.</p>
               <p>To proceed on this ſubject, I have in my ſecond Paper, and ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, ſet down certain Texts, which according to St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> at large on the firſt of <hi>Titus,</hi> do plead the identity of a Presbyter and a Biſhop, and from him made uſe of by others. Now I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49405:35"/>will take a <hi>Note</hi> or two thereon, which will come in fitly here, as the fartheſt way perhaps about, but the neereſt way home of ſaying ſomething to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this buſineſs.</p>
               <p>The one Note is this; that, As thoſe places on one hand do ſhake Epiſcopacy, if preſſed <hi>ſtrictly, Jure Divino:</hi> So do they on the other hand go farther, and take the Lay-Elder clean away; which while ſome have preſſed as ſtrictly in Presbytery, it would not paſs. A Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter (or Elder) is all one with a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in Scripture: But there was never heard of a Lay-Biſhop, (a Lay-Paſtor) and conſequently, no Lay-Elder; I mean, as to ruling Eccleſiaſtically in Eccleſiaſtical affairs; for if there were any, as to deciding of quarrels, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Brethrens going to Law, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 1 <hi>Cor. 6.</hi>) that, I ſuſpect, was all. When there are no qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions layed down by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. where he directs about the making Church officers, but only of the Biſhops and Deacons, as it cuts off the Biſhop
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49405:35"/>from being a diſtinct Order from the Presbyter, ſo does it quite cut away the Lay-Elder.</p>
               <p>For that controverted place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. (which as it is urged, in the <hi>Divine right of Church govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> did hold me under conviction, until this light, of the Presbyter being one with the Biſhop, was clearer than it). I will give you my interpretation; And the rather, becauſe neither of the many, which <hi>Eraſtus, Field, Bilſon, Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, Mead, Sutliffe,</hi> or others, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, to wave that Text againſt Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, could ſatisfie me; as perhaps this of mine may not likewiſe ſatisfie others. Such as it is however, you ſhall have it. The Biſhop and Elder, I have ſaid, are one office, the one name only ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>Induſtriam curae paſtoralis,</hi> the other <hi>Sapientiae maturitatem,</hi> as <hi>Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> out of <hi>Bede:</hi> This office is to rule, and preach; Ruling and preaching are the inſeparable parts of the ſame, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. I ſpeak <hi>quoad</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whatſoever it be ſometimes <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49405:36"/>exercitium.</hi> Now there are ſome, more able for one part of their office, and ſome more able for the other. Thoſe that are <hi>eminent</hi> in either, the Apoſtle would have to be encouraged, or rewarded accordingly. Let them have <hi>double honor,</hi> that is, Not, as ſome do fondly gloſs it, two things, <hi>Reverence,</hi> and <hi>Maintenance;</hi> for the next verſe to this, tells us what honor he cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly means; ſuch as when otherwhere, he ſays, <hi>Honor widows;</hi> that is, Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or proviſion for them; and <hi>double</hi> honor, is, <hi>more</hi> maintenance then others.</p>
               <p>The Emphaſis then for the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, does lye on the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is not to be conſtrued barely <hi>bené</hi> but <hi>pulchrè, egregiè, eminentèr,</hi> (that is the genuine ſignification of the word, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>). And this being put in the beginning emphatically, to the firſt branch, will appear eaſily to him, that ponders the <hi>Greek</hi> Text, that it muſt be underſtood again in the latter, to wit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſcilicet</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo. Here then
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49405:36"/>plainly is the meaning. Thoſe Miniſters that are more eminent then others, are to have more encouragement, <hi>honor</hi> or maintenance <hi>above</hi> others, that is, <hi>double</hi> honor: whether they are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in one part of their Office, or in the other, in ruling, or in preaching, but eſpecially, if they are eminent in preaching.</p>
               <p>The other note I muſt add in the behalf of Epiſcopacy: for if I know any thing by my own heart, it does love integrity, which is the ſpeaking, as nothing but what I find in it, ſo the whole I find there. When I have ſaid above, that, the identity of a Biſhop and a Presbyter in Scripture does <hi>ſhake Epiſcopacy,</hi> if it be held <hi>Jure divino, ſtrictly;</hi> I muſt confeſs alſo, if it be held ſo only <hi>at large,</hi> there does ſome impreſſions, ever ſince my deliberate reading of the Conference at the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> remain upon me for it, By a <hi>Jus divinum</hi> I underſtand vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly, <hi>juſtum &amp; juſsum</hi> in the Word of God. It is true, there is no ſuperiority of the Biſhop above the Presbyter in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49405:37"/>Scripture, becauſe they were all one then, two words for the ſame thing; but yet there is a ſuperiority and inferiority in the Scripture among the Miniſters in the Church. The Biſhops ſuperiority is not <hi>jure divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> but I ſay, <hi>Superiority</hi> is <hi>jure divino.</hi> The twelve Apoſtles were above the Seventy. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in his Church, firſt, ſecondarily, thirdly,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 10.28. Now while the Church had her extraordinary Officers, it did ſuffice, that this ſuperiority and inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority was terminated, or lodged in thoſe divers <hi>orders;</hi> but when that which was extraordinary, was <hi>done away,</hi> and there remained only one Order (the Paſtor and Teacher) of the four (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.) there was in the Church before; then muſt the ſuperiority &amp; inferiority of the preaching Miniſtry, or Prieſt, quite fall: or elſe the Authority of the Church muſt interpoſe, and make a difference of <hi>degree</hi> in identity of <hi>order;</hi> and ſo the names of Biſhop and Presbyter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſit for the turn, were prudently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by pious antiquity, and mad
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49405:37"/>uſe of for it. For man to create a new officer, or another order in his Lords houſe, which himſelf hath not <hi>ſet</hi> there, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28.) cannot, I doubt, be taken well by him. But to put a difference on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of degree, or to double the dignity as well as maintenance, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.) to ſome above others in <hi>the ſame office,</hi> is not like to be at all againſt his will.</p>
               <p>Now then, if you ask me, Is Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy <hi>jure divino,</hi> or no? I anſwer, If you take this <hi>largely,</hi> it is; becauſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, and inferiority in the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſtry of the Church, is of Chriſt, and the Scripture. If you take it <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> it is not; becauſe the diſtinction of a Biſhop and Presbyter is not of Scripture; but this diſparity of <hi>degree</hi> in the ſame <hi>order,</hi> is aſſumed by man, as conſonant to the will of God, in general, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to government. To be more ſhort; Inequality for orders ſake in the Miniſtry, is of <hi>divine;</hi> the <hi>mode,</hi> or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion thereof in Epiſcopacy, is of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical,</hi> inſtitution.</p>
               <p>It appears in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:49405:38"/>and <hi>Titus,</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> writes to them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a rate, that does ſignifie very plainly, an authority in them over the Elders and Deacons in their Churches. How does he tell <hi>Timothy</hi> of his abiding at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to <hi>charge ſome, that they teach no other doctrine?</hi> Why does he lay down qualifications of the Paſtor and Deacon, what they ought to be, and do? What are the duties of other men to him, but upon this account? Wherefore does he bid him, <hi>Rebuke an Elder:</hi> And how ſhall he <hi>receive an accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him by witneſs,</hi> if he had not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, and power of Juriſdiction, over them? <hi>And theſe things I write,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that thou might'ſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the Church of God.</hi> Again, <hi>Do nothing by partiality.</hi> Who does not ſee here, <hi>Epiſcopus paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> as well as <hi>gregis?</hi> Who will not confeſs a preheminence of Authority in <hi>Timothy</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> over the Miniſters there, that is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with every common Presbyter? You may believe it the rather, becauſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49405:38"/>our Divines at the Conference menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, never denyed it. That which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, is this; That <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Evangeliſts: But in the mean time, the thing it ſelf, and matter contended for, is found in Scripture, and granted to be practiſed by theſe two men. And what if they had lived and dyed where <hi>Paul</hi> left them, in the exerciſe of this Authority? Had the continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, changed the nature, and made it evil? Was it lawful for them to exerciſe ſuch a power and juriſdiction for a year? and had it been unlawful, if they had exerciſed it ten, or for their lives? If it had not, there is the whole thing which is diſputed for, in a <hi>fixed</hi> Biſhop. Here then, I take up, and diſtinguiſh; There is the <hi>matter</hi> it ſelf of Epiſcopacy, and the <hi>form</hi> or mode of it. The <hi>matter</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have its warrant in Gods Word: The <hi>form,</hi> which is the breaking a ſingle <hi>order</hi> (to wit, the order of the Paſtor) into two <hi>degrees</hi> in that order, and, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ceaſing of the Evangeliſt, an higher order, the placing his work ſo
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49405:39"/>far as it is ordinary, and continues neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Churches welfare, upon the <hi>ſuperior degree</hi> of the Paſtor ſo divided, is indeed of mans <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</hi> Let then the Biſhop remember, that as he is Paſtor, the Miniſters alſo are Paſtors by God, whoſe office as to their own flock, is to <hi>rule</hi> and to <hi>teach,</hi> as well as his. Let him beware for his life, he does not un-paſtor the <hi>lower degree;</hi> but think rather, how good is help like to be unto burden and work; And then, foraſmuch as the <hi>timber</hi> of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy is cut out of Scripture, though the <hi>ſtructure</hi> it ſelf, and whole <hi>rearing</hi> of it up be of man, and that varyed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to places and times; I ſee no reaſon, but the Presbyterian himſelf may yield to it, with good ſatisfaction. Will you hear the Learned Fathers own arbitration? <hi>Sicut Presbyteri ſciunt ſe ex Eccleſiae conſuetudine, ei qui ſibi praepoſitus fuerit, eſſe ſubjectos: ita Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopi noverint, ſe magis conſuetudine quam diſpoſitionis Deminicae veritate, Presbyteris eſſe majores; &amp; in communi
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49405:39"/>debere Eccleſiam regere, imitantes Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, qui cùm haberet in poteſtate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus praeeſſe populo Iſrael, Septuaginta elegit cum quibus populum judicaret.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49405:40"/>
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>I Have not digreſſed, as I may ſeem, in the preceding Paper; yet ſhall I return more directly on the point, to that which remains, that is, the fourth and laſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. I did not think at firſt of writing half thus much; but loe here, how my ink, like the waters, <hi>riſe</hi> upon me, that there are ſome few Scruples not yet paſſed over. And after this, eſpecially my fourth Paper, What is there more in the ranſack of my ſoul, that all the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is there, can rake up farther againſt this thing? Truly, I find there is ſomething yet methinks ſticks, about that <hi>gift</hi> mentioned with laying on of hands in <hi>Timothy,</hi> with a paſſage (put them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) I have met with lately out of St. <hi>Gregory. Sicut baptizatus ſemel, ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum baptizari non debet; ita qui conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratus eſt ſemel, in eodem iterum ordine, non debet conſecrari.</hi> Here is <hi>argumentum à Simili.</hi> Let my miſgiving thoughts for a while work upon it.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49405:40"/>
               <p>Baptiſm is a Sacrament of initiation into Chriſtianity: So, haply, Ordination into the Miniſtry. In Baptiſm, there is the ſpiritual grace and outward rite: In Ordination, there is an outward rite, and likely this ſpiritual gift. To every functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is a gift apt for the diſcharge of it, annexed to it, and given (when God pleaſe) with it. Why is not Impoſition of hands a ſign and ſeal of this <hi>gift</hi> in the Miniſtry, as waſhing with water of <hi>grace</hi> in baptiſm? <hi>Ceremonia hac eſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm</hi> (ſayes <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>ex Scripturis ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, deinde quam non eſſe inanem nec ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervacuam, ſed fidele ſpiritualis gratiae ſymbolum, teſtatur</hi> Paulus. Inſt. l. 4. c. 19. §. 28. And what if Ordination hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be a very perfect Sacrament, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> of Baptiſm on <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Adverte quàm illud tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſit, &amp; quantum valeant Pontificum impoſitae manus?</hi> ſayes <hi>Theophylact</hi> of Ordination, on 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.14. In the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Canon, where I read of Re-ordination, it is in ſuch a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49405:41"/>caſe only, that required alſo rebapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation; and <hi>in Concilio Capuano, ui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizationes, ita re-ordinationes ſunt prohibitae,</hi> Baron. an. 389. n. 74. quoted by Maſon de Min. Ang. p. 170. In ſhort, a man cannot be born twice, or twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, no more can he be twice bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and conſequently neither twice ordained. Here is the <hi>Herculean</hi> pillars, and I gueſs, the <hi>non ultrà</hi> of my doubts.</p>
               <p>For anſwer whereunto, I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe one thing, that the Conſcience is ſolely Gods Prerogative; and, as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſo we ought not to ſuffer it, to be bound by the authority of man (I mean, ſo far as to make any matter in it ſelf ſin) where it is left free by his Word. Let that of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> to this purpoſe, be heeded, <hi>Quod de Scripturis authoritatem non habet, eadem facilitate contemnitur quâ probatur.</hi> This premiſed, the Solution here, does lye in the rejecting ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions as theſe, which are too high ſtrained, and not conſonant to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Doctrine of the Proteſtants, who admit only two Sacraments upon grand
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49405:41"/>reaſon, and that there cannot therefore be a parity of Ordination with Baptiſm, as I have framed. To unravel the ſame then, let me take a little ſcope. There are three things (ſay our Divines) muſt go to a Sacrament; <hi>Symbolum externum, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina inſtitutio,</hi> and <hi>promiſsio gratiae.</hi> For the firſt, it is manifeſt in Ordination. For the ſecond, an authentick Divine hath theſe words: <hi>Licèt nullum extet certum praeceptum</hi> (which yet in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. is implyed, ſays <hi>Walaeus</hi>) <hi>de manuum impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitione; quia tamen fuiſſe in perpetuo uſu Apoſtolis videmus, illa tam accurata eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum obſervatio praecepti vice nobis eſſe debet.</hi> Cal. Inſt. l. 4. c. 3. §. 16. For the laſt, <hi>promiſsio gratiae;</hi> we muſt know there is a double grace. The grace of the Covenant (as I may ſay) and Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al grace, that is, endowment for our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to profit others: When Divines tell us of a <hi>promiſe of grace,</hi> which muſt go with the Precept, to make a Sacrament; we are to take <hi>Grace</hi> ſtill, in the firſt ſenſe, the grace of the Goſpel: and ſo, <hi>No</hi> Ceremony, Rite, or Inſtitution (Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical, or otherwiſe) which is not to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49405:42"/>be received of Chriſtians <hi>pro ſigillo juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fidei,</hi> Rom. 4.11. or <hi>pro ſigno gratiae juſtificantis,</hi> that is, which does not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, conſign, and confer to us remiſſion of ſins, and ſalvation upon our believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>can</hi> be no Sacrament, in the ſtrict and right notion of it with us.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>gift</hi> then given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> which hath come in play before, upon ſuppoſition, his office was thereby meant, (for ſo the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7.) calls <hi>Miniſtery, Teaching,</hi> gifts) and waved in the ſenſe, that it muſt now come in again to be conſidered here, namely, as it may be taken for <hi>grace (gratìs data)</hi> or a faculty to diſcharge his office, and ſo lies ſtill upon our hands: Let us note, that it is ſaid manifeſtly to be given <hi>by Propheſie.</hi> By Propheſie no doubt (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18.) is meant divine revelation; If by this gift then, were meant his office, (as the more judicious ſtill hold) it denotes, that <hi>Paul</hi> was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by revelation (as we read the like, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1, 2.) to ordain <hi>Timothy</hi> a Miniſter. <hi>Spiritus Sanctus oraculo</hi> Timotheum <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinaverat
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49405:42"/>ut in ordinem Paſtorum co-op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taretur,</hi> ſayes <hi>Calvin in locum.</hi> If by the Gift, is meant <hi>Grace,</hi> Miniſterial Grace, or a ſpecial talent for his office, then muſt it import, that <hi>Paul</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Spirit of Propheſie (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in himſelf, or others) that ſuch a gift, talent, or doubling his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, would be beſtowed on <hi>Timothy</hi> from God upon this Ceremony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he layes his hands on him; And then it does appear, that this Text (or Texts) cannot (no more then that, where Chriſt breathes on his Diſciples) afford us a ſolid ground, to conclude any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of grace, or gift (ſuch gift) to be annexed to this rite for any others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide him. I ſay, if <hi>Paul</hi> does expect this gift, to be given to <hi>Timothy</hi> upon this action, from revelation, then cannot we ground upon this, any connexion of this gift to the rite, without the like <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie going before on us;</hi> or ſome other Scripture, that holds forth the promiſe thereof to us in the uſe of the ſaid Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony; which ſeeing we have not, not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49405:43"/>can be pretended otherwhere, there is left us the pure inſtitution, without any thing at all in it Sacramental, to ſcare or terrifie us in this matter. <hi>Similitudo ſolvitur</hi> (ſays the School) <hi>oſtensâ diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſay; In the Sacraments, Grace is ſuppoſed, and then the outward rite is the ſign and ſeal of it. When Circumciſion is ſaid to be the Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Which he had</hi> before <hi>while un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed.</hi> So muſt this Gift be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the perſon to be ordained, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that it is to be tryed firſt, and found in him: and underſtanding it of the talent it ſelf firſt given, and not of the improvement, This Impoſition of hands is <hi>teſſera minimè fallax ejus gratiae,</hi> and cannot be iterated, becauſe Baptiſm cannot (which is the argument at firſt) or for the reaſon only (whatſoever that is) thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Let us know clearly, that the bottom of the abſurdity, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the iteration it ſelf of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49405:43"/>by Schoolmen and Fathers, will be found to lye in an opinion flat contrary hereunto; to wit, that the Sacraments confer grace; and conſequently initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace (or regenerating grace) which is conferr'd by Baptiſm, being not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to be conferred any more then once, Baptiſm can be but once: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thoſe Divines, that after <hi>Calvin</hi> taking the Sacraments only for Confirmations of our Faith, do make Baptiſm only to ſign, ſignifie, and ſeal the grace which we have, and not confer it, the abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is vaniſhed from hence (and muſt be found out elſewhere): for there is no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity at all, to teſtifie, ſeal, or ſignifie the ſame grace more then once. The Lords Supper does ſignifie, ſeal, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the very ſame benefits of the Covenant (ſealed and ſignified by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) to the believer twenty times over. Thoſe that were circumciſed and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in <hi>Johns</hi> and Chriſts dayes, had the ſame initiatory grace ſealed and ſignified to them twice. If this Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then of hands, be only <hi>ſymbolum,</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49405:44"/>or <hi>teſſera,</hi> to ſignifie, teſtifie, or declare ſuch a gift, or faculty in a perſon (alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy received), there is no abſurdity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, and ſignifie it as often as there is good occaſion.</p>
               <p>If indeed, the firſt talent it ſelf, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal gift adapting us for the office, could be tyed to this Rite, as the certain means of conferring it (as they thought of Baptiſmal Regeneration, that it was ſtill conferred by Baptiſm, and never without it); then were there that abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in Re-ordination, as the Schools con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in Re-baptization. But ſeeing,
<list>
                     <item>1. There is no ſuch promiſe as annexes this gift to the rite.</item>
                     <item>2. It were miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, if ſo given.</item>
                     <item>3. It is againſt univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal experience.</item>
                     <item>4. This gift it to be found in the ordained, or elſe they are not to be admitted.</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Timothy</hi> no doubt was endowed with ability (and that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent) before, being trained up from a child to the Scripture.</item>
                     <item>6. The grace that is obtained hereby (to wit, <hi>precibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, non virtute Signi</hi>) is Gods grace <hi>with us,</hi> or bleſſing upon our ſtudies and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49405:44"/>work, and encreaſe of talents (if you will) thereupon, and no otherwiſe.</item>
                  </list> In ſhort, ſeeing this is diſproved other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and from the firſt reaſon above, which is more eſpecially of force; I do perceive that, that which hath troubled me as an objection, will turn to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſerve but the fuller to lay open the nature of Ordination, which is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needful.</p>
               <p>The truth is, with much beating here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, I do ſee plainly, This ſolemnity doth both theſe things; It ſignifies this gift, and impetrates a bleſſing. When a man comes to be ordained, he is to be examined; This Examination (if we know what it is), is, whether he hath this Gift, which is his call from God: When this is found, if you will ſay this ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is a <hi>Sacrament</hi> hereof, in a large ſenſe, as a <hi>viſible</hi> publique ſign or token atteſting, ſignifying and declaring this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward inviſible Miniſterial grace in the perſon to the Church, for its proper end; <hi>Mentem teneas</hi> (with <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>linguam corrigas,</hi> it is but the ſame our Divines ſay, <hi>Ordination is the confirmation of his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49405:45"/>Call,</hi> or may help us well to underſtand it.</p>
               <p>There is then a double call. A call from men, and the call of God. A mans call from men, lyes in their choice of him for their Miniſter, or his title to a place. Whileſt moſt have bin poring upon this outward call by men, the true notion of Ordination hath been out of ſight. Hence Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> (with others commonly) <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopalis Ordinatio Miniſtri ſine titulo, eſt ae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ridicula, ac ſi quis maritus ſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur eſſe, abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> uxore.</hi> But it is a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſtake. A man may be ordained, I think, to the <hi>work,</hi> as to a <hi>place.</hi> Heads, and Fellows of Colledges, cannot but be ſuppoſed to be ordained without abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity. There are Teachers as well as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in the Church. The bottom of the miſ-apprehenſion then, lyes here: when theſe Divines have ſaid well, That Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination is this <hi>declaration</hi> only, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of a mans call, they dream of this outward call only, this call by men, and ſo are out. The call of God then, in the next place, does lye no doubt in this Gift, apt to diſcharge the function; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7, 8, 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49405:45"/>15.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21.) a fitneſs for the Miniſtry; when God gives a man endowments, with a heart for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. This is his Call and Commiſſion from Chriſt, which, it is his Prerogative too only to give. This now, is tryed by the Ordainers, The rule is, <hi>Lay hands on no man ſuddenly.</hi> That meddles not, I think, (unleſs occaſionally) with the mans title to his Living, but his qualifications, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, abilities, whether he hath this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward call, the commiſſion and talent from our Lord, that we may own him as a fellow ſervant in this work. When this is found, What is Ordination then real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (as hath been before mentioned), but the <hi>declaring</hi> or approving of the perſon accordingly, as indeed ſo called, endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fit, (or, as indeed, commiſſioned, from the Maſter himſelf) by this ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? and ſo hath he not <hi>ſpiritualem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem,</hi> his Miniſterial power and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (which is derived upon him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by vertue of Chriſts will declared in his Word, that ſuch as are ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſhould be Officers to him; or rather, leaſt we be too nice, by vertue of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49405:46"/>full call of the Inſtitution, gift, and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent together) beſtowed on him by the hands of man, (for he is the Embaſſador alone of Chriſt and God, and not of men) but <hi>confirm'd</hi> to him hereby: which it does, 1. In recommending him to God for his grace, wherein we beleive it, not to be <hi>profanus ritus,</hi> or <hi>inutile ſignum,</hi> but expect accordingly his bleſſing both upon our ſtudies and our work. 2. In conciliating to him an authority in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of men, that his Miniſtry is <hi>received</hi> thereupon by all in the Church; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (let me ſay) the eſſence, or quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence, of all that which dare be arroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by mortal man, as what <hi>he</hi> indeed contributes, or does, to the <hi>making</hi> of a man <hi>Chriſts Miniſter,</hi> when it is through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed, will be found to lye at laſt. And thus hath <hi>ſilver</hi> the Tower-ſtamp, and Dignities are made <hi>currant</hi> by their proper ceremonies and cuſtoms, wherein all concerned may take notice of them.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe now, this being the whole of Ordination, our ſcruples may end (and that beſt) in the nature of the thing only; For who is ſo dull, that he cannot apply
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49405:46"/>this? Nevertheleſs, in regard that the compariſon with Baptiſm, is that which hath ſtuck with the moſt (and may ſtill perhaps) at the bottom, I ſhall add one thing more, which will fetch that <hi>thorn</hi> too, quite out; provided you will pardon me, if the Needle be thruſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nearer then I would elſe, to the quick, for to do it. Let us turn then to the 19. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and we ſhall find there certain Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> who were baptized unto <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm: It is like, that <hi>Apollos</hi> living there, a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Teacher (and knowing only the baptiſm of <hi>Iohn, Act.</hi> 18.24, 25.) had bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized them. Now we are to know, that this baptiſm having the ſame Author, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25. Matter, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.26. Form, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.32, 33.34. Ends, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.3. And conſigning the ſame Goſpel, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.3, 4. was but <hi>one</hi> with Chriſts baptiſm, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore catechizing them herein, thus inſtructs them; <hi>John verily baptized with the baptiſm of repentance, ſaying, unto the people, that they ſhould believe on him, which ſhould come after him, that is,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>on Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49405:47"/>It follows, <hi>when they heard this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Now the queſtion ariſes here, who are meant by <hi>they</hi> in the Text? The people unto whom <hi>John</hi> ſpake, or the perſons (the twelve men) to whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks? not the firſt certainly, becauſe then muſt theſe words <hi>[that is, on Chriſt Jeſus]</hi> be <hi>John</hi>'s interpretation, when it is plain, he did not know Chriſt by his name, when he baptized, until Chriſt himſelf came to him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.30, 31. Who are they then? Why, the <hi>laſt,</hi> no doubt. For <hi>John,</hi> and his Diſciples did baptize <hi>into one which ſhould come</hi> (as it is ſaid here): but it was the Apoſtles and Chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that baptized expreſly, <hi>in the name of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To wave this, ſome learned men (as Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi>) do accept <hi>Calvins</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, who by <hi>baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> would have meant, Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt. The learned Annotations of the Aſſembly, ſeeing this quite incredible, would have invented this other way; but I will ſet you down Mr. <hi>Diodates</hi> very faithful
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49405:47"/>Annotation. <hi>After</hi> Paul <hi>had largely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them, touching the correſpondence of</hi> John <hi>with Chriſt, they formally were baptized in the name of Chriſt; for there was no inconvenience to confirm</hi> Johns <hi>extraordinary baptiſm, with the ordinary and more expreſs baptiſm of Chriſt, ſeeing God would have them who had received the old ſeal of the Covenant, namely, Circumciſion, to receive the new one of Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this place then, I ſhall advance this truth, that quite rids the whole doubt, at leaſt as to the hainouſneſs (in hand) of our conceit, in this matter; that, Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the univerſal judgement and currant practiſe of the Church for ſingle baptiſm, be not impeached, but ſtands good in <hi>theſi:</hi> yet is there, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hath</hi> there been (for I will ſpeak ſure) ſome particular reaſon in <hi>hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,</hi> that even this very Sacrament it ſelf of baptiſm (from whence all our dread ariſes) might be twice received, in ſome caſe, by the ſame perſons without ſin; and that when their firſt too remains valid, and not to be renounced, or held
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49405:48"/>null, but only ſome farther end and confirmation, is obtained by the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſhall not need to make applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our caſe, but I will conclude; If this moſt ſolid and judicious Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter laſt quoted, accounts it no inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, to confirm <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſm by baptizing theſe men again <hi>formally</hi> (as he ſpeaks) in the Name of Chriſt: I hope then, there is no ſting left us <hi>à pari,</hi> but we may reſolve more freely (whoſe caſe at this time is particular) that there is no inconvenience neither (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perhaps leſs) for us to confirm our Ordination by Presbytery (or rather, former Miniſtry) by being <hi>formally</hi> (as he has it) or Epiſcopally ordained again to that purpoſe: So that, as we are <hi>verè, rectè, ſecundùm Scripturas, quoad ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtautiam</hi> already, we may alſo become <hi>legalitèr, ritè, ſecundùm Canones, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad circumſtantias &amp; accidentia,</hi> (to wit, <hi>ſecundum conſuetudinem noſtram &amp; ritus Eccleſiae; Ordained Miniſters of our Church</hi> in this Nation. In ſhort, if you will, we had before <hi>Ordinationem legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timam,</hi> and ſo there needs no other to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49405:48"/>be required; but having it not <hi>legitimè,</hi> (or <hi>Canonicè,</hi>) I think, without laying ſtreſs though, on theſe terms, both for the compariſons ſake, as our grounds before) if another be required, a man may without ſin ſubmit to it.</p>
               <p>For thoſe worthy Epiſcopal Divines, that will ſay, Presbyterial Ordination is <hi>vera,</hi> but not <hi>legalis, non tamen iteran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> (as Biſhop <hi>Carlton</hi>) I will underſtand them, that they account as I do, where there is this, it ſuffices by the Word of God ſo as there is no <hi>need</hi> of other, if men would: But if any will take them ſo, that in no caſe there may be no other; Let them take heed, them do not make more ſin and law then God hath made.</p>
               <p>When a thing is good in its ſelf, the repetition can be evil only in being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, or more than needs; Now I ſay, though as to the part of our Rulers, who might take the opinion, that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Ordination is valid as former Biſhops have done, Re-ordination in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, is more then needs; (Let them take heed that impoſe it): Yet, as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49405:49"/>for our part, when it is plainly ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it is, it ceaſes to us, to be more then needs; and then Obedience to Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, in things not forbidden by God, is a ground of action. You will ſay, things indifferent, become prohibited in caſe of ſcandal. I anſwer, there is <hi>ſcandalum datum</hi> we know, and <hi>ſcandalum accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> Though there be here really (I fear) as to the part of the Requirer, <hi>Offence given;</hi> yet as to the part of the Submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (I hope in mercy) it is <hi>Offence</hi> only <hi>taken.</hi> I may add more aſſuredly, we ſhall indeed <hi>give</hi> offence, if many of us do otherwiſe. <hi>Cum Romam venio, jejuno Sabbatho; cùm hic ſum, non jejuno. Sic etiam tu</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi>) <hi>ad quam fortè Eccleſiam veneris, ejus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſerva, ſi cuiquam non vis eſſe ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalo, nec quenquam tibi.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49405:49"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>I Have done, and I hope, you will not think any of theſe things to be tedious, or out of <hi>neceſſary</hi> order; If you do, I remember the Comaedian, that there is a <hi>negligence</hi> ſometime to be imitated, rather then an <hi>obſcure diligence.</hi> I muſt confeſs, I am tyred for once, in digging the <hi>mettal;</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever of it, ſhall paſs the fire when it is tryed, may be put into a new <hi>mould</hi> with leſs labour, to him that ſhall have uſe of it.</p>
               <p>There is one thing only I would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe now at laſt, as hugely conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in my ſlender opinion, at this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in regard of the multitudes invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our caſe, as alſo for ſuch as may come over at any time to us from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches, that for the removing of offence and ſcruple altogether, unto
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49405:50"/>the forms of ordering of Deacons and Prieſts, there were a new added, for the Confirmation by the Biſhop, of ſuch of them, who have yet been ordained by Presbyters only, which ſhould be made to run in ſuch a ſtrain; that we may ſay of it, as <hi>Suarez</hi> does of the Ordination of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas. Haec manuum Impoſitio nobis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum deprecatoria, non etiam conſecrato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria videtur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let all things</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>be done in decency and order;</hi> Now it ſeems a thing not agreeable to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he which is a Prieſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſhould be forced back and made a Deacon. You may ſay, If this be a breach of order, how could I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it? I anſwer, if I askt how it can be required, it were more to the purpoſe. <hi>Non oportet ut qui ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores ordines ſuſceperunt, minores pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs habuerint; quanquam ſic ordinatè or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines conferri ſtatuerit Eccleſia, ut pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs minores deinde majores ſuſcipiantur.</hi> Aq. Sup. q. 35.50. It is no queſtion,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49405:50"/>but a Prieſt may be a Deacon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Church of a Deacon makes a Prieſt; and I was not ordained a Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con before. But that which I have to ſpeak hereto, and that ſatisfiedly, is: Matters of order (I hope) muſt give place to matters of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; If the Church does ſtand upon it, it is <hi>pro formâ</hi> only, and I do but obſerve order, in breaking it. As for us, let our Rulers look to this, we do but vail our heads to Obedience, to Uniformity, to Peace, to Neceſſity. What if my <hi>Ordinary</hi> be of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I am no Miniſter, if or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained only by the Presbytery (as hath been intimated before) which, by the way, if he is, I am convinced, do what I can for all that, it is an error; for, it is one thing, to hold Ordination ought to be by a Biſhop, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that no Ordination, is good and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid otherwiſe. <hi>Quod fieri non debet</hi> it ſelf, <hi>factum valet.</hi> Yet does ſober <hi>Davenant</hi> quote <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> telling us, that when ſome in his time were ordained only
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49405:51"/>by Presbyters they judged them in <hi>Laicos redire,</hi> when yet he has his <hi>Ego non auſim</hi> (before) in the ſame <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> And what if accordingly, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my people will not own me, but clamour; They will not receive the Sacraments from me; I am no Miniſter, and ought not to preach? Nay, what if my ſelf do queſtion whether I am a Miniſter of <hi>England,</hi> though a Miniſter of Chriſt, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though <hi>verè</hi> a Miniſter, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am yet <hi>legalitèr</hi> ſo, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Church? And what then, if they will make me Church-warden or Conſtable? Yea, to ſpeak more gravely, What if they do thus (as before mentioned) ſome out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and others pretend it? Who does not ſee here, that the ſtopping the mouths of gain-ſayers, the cutting off occaſion from thoſe that ſeek it, the ſatisfying the ſober, and letting my Miniſtry have its <hi>free courſe,</hi> is a matter of more conſequence then this whole buſineſs, that we ſhould
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49405:51"/>ſcruple ſo much at it? The Lord ſtill keep in me a tender frame, and ſerious ſpirit; but deliver me from a ſcanty ſoul, and too ſcrupulouſly-ſuperſtitious conſcience.</p>
               <p>And here, methinks, my heart is enlarged towards many of my pious Brethren, that need relief; and who, I am perſwaded, <hi>If they did know,</hi> (as Chriſts ſpeaks) <hi>but what that meaneth, I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice,</hi> would not haply <hi>condemn the guiltleſs,</hi> that is themſelves, that for the continuance, or the <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> their Miniſtry, do ſubmit to this thing, <hi>Re-ordination.</hi> Provided ſtill, they may crave remedy, if it be clogg'd with any circumſtance againſt their conſcience; which at preſent may be attained, I preſume, according to his Majeſties Declaration. <hi>Then</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tathias <hi>and his friends ſaid one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, If we ſhall all do as our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, have done, and not defend our ſelves upon the Sabbath, then will they come upon us, and take our place; then
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49405:52"/>ſhall others poſſeſs the Sanctuary, and incontinently upon our ſcruple, rid us from the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Deo Gloria, mihi Condonatio.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 1660.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your unworthy Fellow-ſervant in the Miniſtry, <hi>J. H.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Neh. 13.21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Remember me, O my God, concerning this alſo, and ſpare me accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the greatneſs of thy mercy.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:49405:52"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
